Today's דף daf is in memory of our dear friend Joe Gutman
who passed away yesterday.
He was a long time member of the דף daf and he'd
been through it more than I think this was his second cycle
at least or whatever. I think this is his 30th. 30th. Wow.
So we really feel his loss and
he'll be with us in spirit. We pick up on דף צ
עמוד ב Daf Tzadi Amud Bet on the משנה Mishna and we
are dealing with issues about which comes first, so we had that
everything that is תדיר tadir that is more regular comes first and
then everything that is holier comes first. Of course holier is a
harder scale to measure than more regular.
And now we pick up with the משנה Mishna here on the
bottom of דף צ עמוד ב. Daf Tzadi Amud Bet. כל החטאות
שבתורה קודמין לאשמות. Kol hachataot shebatorah kodmin la'ashamot. All of the sin
offerings come before the אשמות, ashamot, the guilt offerings, because the חטאת
chattat has four applications of blood and the אשם asham only two.
חוץ מאשם מצורע. chutz me'asham metzora. But if you have to choose
between an אשם asham of a מצורע metzora and a חטאת, chattat,
you let the מצורע metzora come first מפני שהוא בא על ההכשר
mipnei shehu ba al hachshair because that is coming to allow him
to get out of his מצורע metzora status and to allow him
to come into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash etc. So it's interesting
different ways you can conceptualize that, right? I mean you could say
it raises a person, it gives them access to the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, but a חטאת chattat atones for somebody's sin, so why
is this so? To me it sort of signifies a certain aspect
of, well first of all a מצורע metzora is pushed outside the
community in the way a normal sinner is not,
and also even if it just talks about access to the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash or whatever, it still speaks about the difference between
personal sin which is metaphysical and between you and God and so
on as opposed to a state which impacts your practical role within
the community. So I think it speaks very powerfully in terms of
giving precedence and recognizing the more urgent need of that.
כל האשמות שבתורה, Kol ha'ashamot shebatorah, it's sort of like how they
teach you how to make this chart about important, not important, and
urgent, not urgent, or whatever. Some things are a question about importance
versus urgency, right?
Okay. כל האשמות שבתורה באין בני שתים. Kol ha'ashamot shebatorah ba'in bnei
shtayim. All the אשמות ashamot in the תורה Torah have to be
two years old. ובאין בכסף שקלים. Uva'in bechesef shekalim. It's basically a
פסוק pasuk by some and then we apply it to others. And
they have to be a minimum of two שקל shekel cost.
חוץ מאשם נזיר ואשם מצורע. chutz me'asham nazir ve'asham metzora. The exceptions
are אשם נזיר asham nazir and אשם מצורע, asham metzora, again based
on פסוקים. pesukim. שהן באין בני שנתן, shehen ba'in bnei shnatan, that
they're one year old, ואין באין בכסף שקלים, ve'ein ba'in bechesef shekalim,
and they do not have to be two שקלים. shekalim. Okay, so
that's like a parenthetical statement about אשמות ashamot when that's not directly
about this issue about precedence.
Now back to the issue about
precedence, is that what? Precedence is like a legal thing. But anyway,
the principle about which comes first.
כשם שקודמין בהקרבתן קודמין באכילתן. Kesheim shekodmin behakravatan kodmin be'achilatan.
Now the same things that come first that are supposed to be
offered first, everything that we've been mentioning until now, also have to
come first,
eaten first. So whatever the priority is, קדשי קדשים kadshei kadashim eaten
before קדשים קלים. kadashim kalim. You know, all the different priorities.
שלמים של אמש ושלמים של יום. Shelamim shel emesh veshelamim shel yom.
Let's say you have a שלמים shelamim that was brought yesterday and
a שלמים shelamim that was brought today. שלמים
של אמש קודמין לשלמים של יום. Shelamim shel emesh kodmin leshelamim shel
yom. Yesterday's come before today's. Now what do you mean by yesterday?
So the simplest point that this means it was slaughtered yesterday, and
that's why it gives the example by שלמים. shelamim. So then of
course that gets back to the question of
urgency, that the one that has been started eating yesterday, it's more
urgent, you gotta finish it right before sunset, so of course you
gotta prioritize that
over the ones that are just brought today. But based on a
later גמרא, Gemara, רש״י Rashi interprets this differently, it's based on the
גמרא Gemara that's coming up. So if you look at רש״י Rashi
for example, רש״י Rashi says שלמים shelamim two lines down in the
wide lines of
רש״י: Rashi: שלמים שבאו
אמש לעזרה ושהו עד היום ושחטן. shelamim sheba'u emesh la'azarah veshah'u ad
hayom veshachatan. Okay, so he says that they're hanging out there, the
animals were there. I mean one wonders, let's say a guy came
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash he brought his קרבן korban and
there was a long line and they say come back tomorrow. You
imagine he takes his קרבן korban back with him home and then
he brings it back the next day? I don't know, do they
have a number?
Maybe they took the קרבן korban from him and they said thank
you, we'll get to this, and then he left and then they
were left. I mean, so it's hard to even imagine the scenario,
right? But then it's also hard to imagine, so why does it
come first? So then it just comes first because it's been hanging
out and it's like inappropriate that we make it wait longer. Of
course then it didn't have to be a שלמים, shelamim, it could
have talked about a חטאת, chattat, as long as the animal is
alive. So it's certainly not
פשט peshat of
the
משנה. Mishna.
Wait, maybe the reason is because they're focusing on the ritual in
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's a matter of just you eating
it, and that sort of shifts the focus.
No, but we just introduced eating. כשם שקודמים בהקרבתן קודמים באכילתן. Keshem
shekodmim behakravasan kodmim beachilasan. So I think specifically because we introduced the
issue of eating makes it sound
that it is talking about that. Okay.
But you are right, if we're talking about eating, then we're talking
about the owners eating the שלמים, Shlomim, and then we'd have to
talk about you brought two שלמים, Shlomim, you brought a שלמים Shlomim
yesterday and you brought it today, and you got a ton of
meat going on in your house now. But anyway, I hear that
point too. Okay. לשיום, Leshoyom, שלמים של אמש חטאת ואשם של היום.
Shlomim shel emesh chatas ve'asham shel hayom.
Now
let's say you have yesterday's שלמים Shlomim and today's חטאת Chatas and
אשם, Asham, so that's a clear... so you have the one hand,
either the issue of urgency by the שלמים, Shlomim, or certainly as
רש"י Rashi explains, that the animal's been standing around. Certainly the issue
of disrespect that you're letting it stay around for so long. But
you have the higher קדושה kedusha of the חטאת Chatas and the
אשם. Asham.
This one's probably speaking about again, מקריב, Makreiv, because again, if the
owners
eat the שלמים, Shlomim,
but the כהנים Kohanim eat the חטאת Chatas and the אשם, Asham,
it wouldn't really be much of a...
Right, that's a good point, that's a good point. The fact that
we're dealing with... we moved into this, presumably you're talking about... it's
just parenthetical. No, I understand. I understand your point. Okay. So that's
a good point why to read this that it's not talking about
the eating because then you don't have a scenario, a simple scenario
where the same people are eating the שלמים Shlomim and they're eating
the חטאת Chatas and the אשם. Asham. That's a good point. Okay,
anyway, you have this issue that it's been standing around since yesterday,
so it's a little bit disrespectful to keep it waiting another day.
But you have the חטאת Chatas and the אשם, Asham, which are
holier. Okay, so the הלכה halacha is: שלמים של
אמש חטאת ואשם של היום שלמים של אמש קודמין דברי רבי מאיר.
Shlomim shel emesh chatas ve'asham shel hayom Shlomim shel emesh kodmin divrei
Rebbe Meir. So רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says, yeah, but the שלמים
Shlomim was here yesterday, you gotta finish that up and take care
of it. וחכמים אומרים חטאת קודמת מפני שהיא קודש קדשים. VeChachamim omrim
chatas kodemes mipnei shehi kodesh kodashim. No, here we give precedence to
the thing that is holier. So that's similar to the גמרא's Gemara
questions the other day, what happens when you have to compete between...
well, actually, we're going to see it's going to be a particular
focus today when you have to compete between different standards. Okay, regular
comes first, holy comes first. What happens when regular competes with holy?
Okay, anyway, here you have what happens when holy competes with stuff
that's been pushed aside. You make the regular holy.
There you go, good מוסר. mussar. Anyway, stuff that's been pushed aside,
which one of
these standards is going to win out? וכולן, Vechulan, now, talking about
just סתם stam eating, now we're again, sort of digressing again because
the whole focus here is priorities, but now that we mentioned about
eating, this really this next line really totally belongs earlier when we
spoke about how are you supposed to remember what you did different
with each קרבן? korban? And how who would eat them, when it
would be eaten and so on. So that's where this next line
belongs. וכולן הכהנים רשאים לשנות באכילתן. Vechulan hakohanim resha'in leshanos beachilasan. They
can eat them however they want.
שלוקין, shelukin, צלויין, tzeluyim, מבושלים, mevushalim, cooked, לתת לתוכן תבלין חולין ותבלין
תרומה דברי רבי שמעון. latet lesochon tavlin chullin vetavlin terumah divrei Rebbe
Shimon. They can put into them spices, whether they're סתם stam spices
or תרומה terumah spices. That's what רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says. רבי
מאיר אומר לא יתן לתוכן תבלין תרומה. Rebbe Meir omer lo yiten
letochan tavlin terumah.
Even in the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash?
In the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, yeah. Because you can't take the
חטאת Chatas out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. לא יתן לתוכן
תבלין תרומה מפני שלא יביא את התרומה לידי פסול. Lo yiten letochan
tavlin terumah mipnei shelo yavi et haterumah lidei pesul. Because then the
תרומה terumah absorbs the taste of the קדשים kodashim and then you...
if you don't eat... and then you're going to limit the time
to be eating the תרומה. terumah. Now if you think about
little flakes of pepper, it's harder to imagine what he's talking about.
But I mean it is, but anyway, but you also think about
תבלין tavlin includes just let's say a whole thing of... a whole
onion, a whole clove of garlic. Right? So this thing now, you
got this onion sitting here and now because it absorbs these קדשים
kodashim juices, you're going to have... you have only a day to
eat it. Okay, so anyway, that's his concern about מביא קדשים לידי
פסול. mevi kodashim lidei pesul. We had that before. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו... Ibayu lehu...
A question before we go? Yeah. On the back to the משנה
Mishna about the cost of the אשם. Asham. That's a minimum price?
Minimum.
Okay. איבעיא להו, Ibayu lehu, they raised the following question. Okay, since
this is a little bit reflects some of the choosing that went
on in the משנה Mishna between yesterday and today versus holy and
so on. תדיר ומקודש איזה מהם קודם? Tadir u'mekudash eizeh meihem kodem?
Okay, you have the more regular versus the holy. Which one are
you going to give precedence to? תדיר קודם משום דתדיר או דילמא
מקודש קודם דקדיש? Tadir kodem mishum detadir o dilma mekudash kodem dekadish?
I love that question. It's like, talk about a way
that didn't really explicate. Do you do תדיר tadir first because it's
תדיר tadir or do you קודש kodesh first because it's קודש? kodesh?
Okay. תמיד קודם. Tamid kodem Good point. תמיד? Tamid Why? Every time
we do every day? All right. תא שמע Ta shema come and
hear... yeah, no, that's the הלכה, halacha, the הלכה halacha is that
the first thing that... no, I'm serious, that's not a choice, the
structure of the הקרבה hakrava in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is
תמיד Tamid? is the very first thing that's brought. Maybe, yeah, maybe,
but it's not evidence enough. תא שמע Ta shema come and hear.
We have to bring something where we actually understand that we have
a choice, that הלכה halacha didn't predictate and we're going to choose.
תא שמע Ta shema come and hear. תמידים קודמין למוספין... Temidim kodmin
le'musafin... so actually, I spoke too soon because here we go, the
actual first evidence it brings is actually... Exactly Michael's case. Okay, a
תמיד tamid comes before the מוסף, Musaf, ואף על גב דמוספין קדישי,
v'af al gav d'musafin kadishi, and even though the מוסף Musaf we're
assuming that because it's let's say a מוסף Musaf of שבת, Shabbat,
it has greater קדושה kedusha because שבת Shabbat is identified, it's more
identified with שבת. Shabbat. You know, it has the שבת Shabbos identity
is somehow part of the מוסף. Musaf. Okay, we don't just call
it a חטאת Chatas or an עולה, Olah, עולה Olah I should
say. Okay, it's עולת שבת. Olat Shabbat. And that gives it a
certain level of קדושה kedusha that doesn't exist by the תמיד. Tamid
And nevertheless, you still do the תמיד Tamid. first. ואף על גב
דמוספין קדישי, V'af al gav d'musafin kadishi, says גמרא Gemara says, אטו
שבת למוספין אהני, לתמידין לא אהני? Atu Shabbos l'musafin ahani, l'temidim lo
ahani? What, do you just think that the שבת Shabbos identity attaches
to the מוסף? Musaf? It also attaches to the תמיד. Tamid Today
it's the תמיד Tamid. of שבת. Shabbos. Which is funny, you sort
of did understand the question, like the answer's not so convincing. Anyway,
it is interesting, right, why the גמרא Gemara jumps to that case.
Why didn't it just say, you know, what I think was Michael
was asking really before you even got to מוסף. Musaf. Why don't
you say we already established that a חטאת Chatas comes before an
עולה, Olah, and yet the עולת תמיד Olat Tamid comes before the
חטאת, Chatas, the first thing you bring is the עולת תמיד, Olat
Tamid, right? So yeah, so the fact that the תמיד Tamid comes
first thing in the morning I'm not so impressed with because again
then you could just ask like on the whole structure. I don't
know why it jumps specifically to the מוסף Musaf of שבת Shabbat
question. Okay, you know, that's an עולה Olah and you still bring
it before you bring other things that are supposed to come before
an עולה. Olah. Anyway, let's take a look at where the גמרא
Gemara goes from this. But the גמרא's Gemara answer here is that
the status of שבת Shabbat applies to the תמיד Tamid as well.
תא שמע Ta shma come in here. מוספי שבת קודמין למוספי ראש
חודש. Musafi Shabbos kodmin l'musafi Rosh Chodesh. Maybe the reason we brought
the תמיד Tamid was in order to get to this question. Okay,
because we're sort of bracketing the תמיד Tamid question, the, you know,
עולת תמיד, Olat Tamid, that's too, that's too much of the general
structure but this is really the question we're getting to. Okay, it's
שבת ראש חודש. Shabbos Rosh Chodesh. All right, and you're going to
bring the מוסף Musaf of שבת Shabbos first. All right, so people
are often bothered right why when it's שבת ראש חודש Shabbos Rosh
Chodesh do you say the שמונה עשרה Shmone Esrei of ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh and insert שבת. Shabbos. The logic right of
תמיד Tamid קודם kodem.
should mean that you should say the שבת Shabbos and insert something
of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So anyway, so שבת Shabbos is both
more תמיד, tamid, now one could also argue that שבת Shabbos is
holier. Right, this is a little strange that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
is seen as holier. רש"י Rashi says well ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
is holier cause it's called מועד. Moed. I don't know why that
should be our standard, you know, here. But anyway.
If you consider the order in the תורה Torah reading also it
comes that.
Right, it could be that that's true also the case. So anyway,
it doesn't seem like it's that relevant but גמרא's Gemara answer is
even if we assume ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is holier cause it's
identity with ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, גמרא's Gemara answer is the same
it gave before. אטו ראש חודש למוספין דידיה אהני, למוסף שבת לא
אהני? Atu Rosh Chodesh l'musafin dideih hani, l'musaf Shabbos lo hani? What,
it also attaches to the identity of the מוספים Musafim of שבת.
Shabbos. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to go through this same question
with the same answer multiple times. תוספות Tosfos says you have to
figure out why the גמרא Gemara didn't accept the answer the first
time, but I have to tell you like I don't find the
answer so convincing. There is a sense in which the identity of
the day is attached, you know, now what you could have said
is that that's not a question of קדושה kedusha of the קרבן.
korban. קדושה kedusha of the קרבן korban is just measured on the
חטאת Chatas עולה Olah etc. level not on its association with the
holy day. But once you are asserting that קדושה kedusha is affected
by its association with the day, obviously the מוסף Musaf of the
יום yom is more associated with the day than a random קרבן
korban that's brought that day.
The מוספים Musafim of שבת Shabbat יום כיפור Yom Kippur which would
come
first? Well the מוסף Musaf of שבת Shabbat or יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur?
Yeah that's a good question. I mean presumably, you know, I mean
we'd have more עליות Aliyot on שבת Shabbat presumably יום כיפור Yom
Kippur is holier like שבת שבתון. Shabbat Shabbaton. תא שמע Ta shma
come in here. מוספי ראשי חודשים, Musafi Roshei Chodashim, doesn't matter the
גמרא's Gemara going to have the same answer for everything. תא שמע
Ta shma מוספי ראשי חודשים קודמין למוספי ראש השנה. Musafi Roshei Chodashim
kodmin l'musafi Rosh Hashana. There you go. ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and
ראש השנה Rosh Hashana always fall on the same day and ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh comes first even though clearly ראש השנה's Rosh Hashana
holier. ואף על גב דראש השנה קדשא. V'af al gav d'Rosh Hashana
kadsha. So גמרא Gemara says, אטו ראש השנה למוסף דידיה אהני, למוסף
ראש חודש לא אהני? Atu Rosh Hashana l'musaf dideih hani, l'musaf Rosh
Chodesh lo hani? So what if it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashana that
קדושה kedusha also attaches one minute to the מוספים Musafim of ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. תא שמע Ta shma okay anyway so that's the
end of the מוספים Musafim evidence where all of the cases actually
seem pretty darn good but the גמרא's Gemara answer is no the
קרבן korban does not have greater קדושה kedusha because it's the קרבן
korban of that day. The קדושה kedusha of the day attaches to
all the קרבנות korbanot that are brought that day. Yes.
Yeah this actually question from Michael in the אשכנזי Ashkenazi ימים נוראים
Yamim Noraim
מוסף עמידה Musaf Amida we don't even mention the קרבן. korban.
Yeah that's based on a different that's based on a different issue.
Yeah that's for ספרדים Sefardim too.
I don't know we're moving
on.
Okay. דבר אחר. Davar acheir. ברכת היין תדירה וברכת היום אינה תדירה.
Birchas hayayin tedira u'birchas hayom eina tedira. Now when you come to
קידוש, Kiddush, right, the famous מחלוקת בית הלל בית שמאי machlokes Beis
Hillel Beis Shammai what do you say first? בורא פרי הגפן Borei
pri hagafen or you know מקדש השבת? mekadesh hashabbat? So here we
basically rule that the ברכה bracha of בורא פרי הגפן borei pri
hagafen comes
first. ותדיר ושאינו תדיר, תדיר קודם. V'tadir v'she'eino tadir, tadir kodem. אף
על גב דברכת
היום... Af al gav d'birchas hayom... קדושה, kedusha, even though מקדש השבת
Mekadesh hashabbat directly associates with שבת, Shabbat, בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri
hagafen is a very generic ברכה. bracha. So even though that represents
greater קדושה, kedusha, it comes second. So that's again like the מוסף
Musaf question, it seems like a pretty good question, and the גמרא
Gemara is going to give the same unconvincing answer. אטו שבת לברכת
היום אהני לברכת היין לא אהני? Atu Shabbas bivirkas hayom ahani livirchas
yayin lo hani? בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri hagafen you could do
actually a good a good a good sermon on this. You know,
even the בורא פרי הגפן, Borei pri hagafen, even the normal things
we do during the rest of the week, on שבת Shabbas they
take on the whole identity of שבת. Shabbat. Your בורא פרי הגפן
Borei pri hagafen on שבת Shabbas is a sort of your eating
on שבת Shabbas is a holier context and so on than your
eating during the week.
So anyway, so it's this is because I always thought this is
making it almost like a ברכת המצוה, birkat hamitzvah, the בורא פרי
הגפן. Borei pri hagafen.
No, why? It's just it's weight, its significance. I don't think the
גמרא Gemara is framing it as a מצוה. mitzvah. I mean that
is an interesting question in general when you have an about about
making a you know do we say יצא מוציא yatza motzi by
בורא פרי הגפן? Borei pri hagafen? It's normally you don't say it
by ברכת הנהנין birchas hanenin but when it's tied in to a
קידוש, Kiddush, you are allowed to say it. Anyway, so there's some
truth to that, but I don't see that in the גמרא Gemara
here. Okay, anyway, so the same good proof and again an answer
which is less convincing than the actual proof. תא שמע, Tashma, come
in here, דאמר רבי יוחנן הלכה מתפלל אדם של מנחה ואחר כך
של מוספין. deamar Rabbi Yochanan halacha mitpalel adam shel Mincha veachar kach
shel Musafin. If it happen ever happens that you know you have
forgotten that it's after חצות chatzot and or actually you know let's
say this happens sometimes on שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret the דאוונען davening
goes on for so long and it's actually already time for מנחה
Mincha and you haven't דאוונט davened מוסף Musaf yet. So which do
you go first? מנחה's Mincha תדיר tadir but מוסף Musaf presumably is
קדוש kadosh because it's associated with the day. And there's a debate
how you פסקן. paskin. So this also can happen when you are
when you wake up at מנחה Mincha time and you realize it
was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh this morning and you forgot to דאוונען
daven and you forgot to דאוונען daven מוסף Musaf and you forgot
to say יעלה ויבא Yaaleh Veyavo שחרית Shacharis in the morning. So
that time what you would do is you would דאוונען daven מנחה
Mincha תשלומין tashlumim of שחרית Shacharis and then מוסף. Musaf. Okay, anyway,
but okay, so anyway, but in this case רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says you דאוונען daven מנחה Mincha first and after that מוסף Musaf
because מנחה's Mincha more תדיר. tadir. So even though מוסף Musaf is
more קדוש. kadosh. So the answer's going to be the same thing.
אטו שבת לתפילת מוספין אהני לתפילת מנחה לא אהני? Atu Shabbas litfillas
Musafin ahani litfillas Mincha lo hani? If
you know if it's a שבת Shabbas let's say and now you're
דאוונען davening מנחה Mincha before מוסף Musaf because it's already after חצות.
chatzot. So the גמרא Gemara says yeah, but it's not that the
מוסף Musaf has a higher קדושה kedusha than מנחה. Mincha. Now that
actually you could hear. Like on שבת Shabbas the מנחה Mincha of
שבת Shabbas itself as opposed to the תמיד, tamid, the מנחה Mincha
of שבת Shabbas does reflect the idea that it is שבת. Shabbat.
Okay, so that's at least you mean the
מנחה Mincha is the תמיד tamid in שבת. Shabbas.
I know, but the נוסח nusach of the מנחה. Mincha. Meaning if
you're talking about the קרבנות, korbanot, the תמיד tamid is the תמיד.
tamid. The נוסח nusach of the מנחה Mincha on שבת Shabbat at
least says מקדש השבת Mekadesh hashabbat in it, you know. So anyway,
okay, but it's the same answer as before. Although yes, all this
does seem to be good evidence that תדיר tadir comes first even
against קדוש, kadosh, the גמרא's Gemara arguing that all these things have
the same קדושה. kedusha. Okay, תא שמע tashma come in here. שלמים
של אמש חטאת ואשם של יום. Shelamim shel emesh chatas veasham shel
yom. Okay, this is what we're getting to. Yesterday's שלמים shelamim and
today's חטאת chatas and אשם. asham.
שלמים של אמש קודמין. Shelamim shel emesh kodmin. So the שלמים shelamim
come first. Now why? It's not קדוש. kadosh. So the גמרא's Gemara
assuming that it's a principle of תדיר. tadir. So I'm sorry, שלמים
של יום, shelamim shel yom, I'm sorry, I misspoke, I spoke too
soon. That's only because it's yesterday's and it's more urgent. האי ואידי
ואידי דיום חטאת ואשם קודמין. Hai idi veidi deyom chatas veasham kodmin.
If they're all today, חטאת chatas and אשם asham come before שלמים.
shelamim. That's obvious, right? That's what like an earlier משנה Mishna said.
You have a שלמים shelamim and a חטאת chatas and an אשם,
asham, you bring a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham before שלמים.
shelamim. Now what so we're setting
שלמים shelamim more תדיר tadir than
well that's that's yes, so that's the גמרא's Gemara going to try
to argue. ואף על גב דשלמים תדירי, Veaf al gav deshelamim tadir,
שלמים shelamim is more תדיר. tadir. Now what does it mean שלמים
shelamim is more תדיר? tadir? It's not like brought on a regular
basis. But the גמרא Gemara so so the גמרא's Gemara answer you're
going to see how it's actually, you know, confusing a concept. אמר
רבא מוציא motzi kamarta wait a minute, שלמים shelamim is not תדיר,
tadir, שלמים shelamim is מצוי, matzui, שלמים shelamim is more common. There
are things that are common, that happen, you know, that are just
there a higher percentage of קרבנות korbanot that are שלמים shelamim on
an average basis there'll be more שלמים shelamim brought on any day
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash than a חטאת chatas and an
אשם. asham. But it doesn't mean it appears with a certain type
of a regularity, okay, and certainly not an
obligatory regularity. I mean even if by even if by chance there's
a שלמים shelamim every day in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right,
you know, there's two concepts, right? One is just the question about,
you know, higher higher phenomenon of it without which doesn't which doesn't
have to mean that there's a regularity of it. But even if
the way the circumstances work out, somebody could report and they've been
doing a statistical study and they've seen that a שלמים shelamim is
there every single day, you know, that it's not שבת Shabbas or
יום טוב, Yom Tov, somebody is bringing a שלמים, shelamim, that still
would be a question whether you call that תדיר tadir because it's
it's a chance regularity. It's not a regularity out of a sense
that it has to be regular. There's no system of regularity about
it. One minute. So תדיר קא מבעיא לן. Tadir kamibaya lan. We're
asking about תדיר, tadir, not about מצוי. matzui. מצוי לא קא מבעיא
לן. Matzui lo kamibaya lan. We're not asking about something's prevalent. If
it's prevalent, that doesn't give it weight, you do the holier one
first. The question's the question is if it's regular, not if it's
more prevalent. Prevalent does not give it weight. Yes, question?
There would have been humongous numbers of שלמים Shlamim during the שלוש
רגלים Shalosh Regalim when the temple stood, but and weren't those considered
a מצוה Mitzvah to eat meat during the festivals?
Yeah, but just... I don't know, it's bringing something... it's... yeah.
The real מצוה Mitzvah is the עולה.
Olah. I mean, שלמי שמחה Shlamim Simcha makes it תדיר. Tadyor. It's
an interesting question. Like if
something... I don't know, yeah, it's an interesting question. Something has a
regularity, but the regularity is three times a year, does that even
give it a status of תדיר? Tadyor? You know, is that more
תדיר Tadyor than something that has absolutely no fixed time? Maybe, it's
an interesting question.
But it's also interesting, like, you know, during the week, let's say,
you know, a שלמים Shlamim is completely voluntary, whereas let's say a
חטאת Chatat and
אשם Asham you have to. Yeah, but חיוב ורשות Chiv v'Reshut is
not part of this scale. No, no, no.
I'm saying in terms of the תדיר, Tadyor, like you'd be thinking
that a lot of people be, you know, they messed up something,
you know what I mean?
You'd be, you know... Yeah, but that's a good point. That is
a good point, like the assumption that שלמים Shlamim is more מצוי.
Matzui. Okay, so, אמר ליה Amlei רב הונא בר יהודה לרבא. Rav
Huna bar Yehuda l'Rava. Oh, we just did that. אטו מצוי לאו
תדיר? Atu matzui lav tadyor? You're saying that מצוי Matzui doesn't get
to be counted as a type of a תדיר? Tadyor? Maybe by
extension? ואתא מהא דתניא בברייתא? V'ata mi tni d'brayta? הוציא את הפסח
שאינו תדיר ולא הוציא את המילה שהיא תדירה. Hotzeis ha'pesach she'eino tadyor
v'lo hotzeis ha'milah she'hi tadyra. So here
basically is a question about how do you know that you... it's
a ברייתא Brayta from תורת כהנים. Torat Kohanim. How do you know
you don't bring a חטאת Chatas for failure to bring a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach or failure to do a ברית מילה Brit Milah
since those are חייב כרת. Chayav Kareis. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara
learns it out because a חטאת Chatas is אשר לא תעשינה, Asher
lo teaseina, only brought for a violation, not brought for a non-fulfillment.
Meaning missed both פסח ראשון ושני?
Pesach Rishon v'Sheni? No, no, no, yeah, yeah, yeah. So anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but maybe I only know to say
that you don't bring a חטאת Chatas for not doing a פסח,
Pesach, which is not so regular, but maybe if you forgot to
do... if you didn't do a מילה, Milah, which is a more
standing obligation, maybe you should bring a חטאת. Chatas. You just do
a מילה, Milah, I understand. Anyway, whatever, so the point is, so
whatever it is, the point is we don't have to worry about
the specifics. The point is just that the גמרא Gemara thinks that
it's more obvious that something should apply to a פסח Pesach because
פסח Pesach is lower on the תדיר Tadyor scale than מילה. Milah.
Okay, but this actually goes to Charlie's point. I mean, פסח Pesach
at least is תדיר Tadyor once a year. I don't know if
that counts as תדיר, Tadyor, but anyway, מילה Milah is completely random
in terms of when it happens. So you see, says the גמרא,
Gemara, that prevalence counts as a type of a תדיר. Tadyor. So
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי תדירה תדירה במצות. Mai tadyra? Tadyra b'mitzvos.
No, here it means it very loosely. This is not the תדיר
Tadyor that would have this question about which comes first. This is
just a question that מילה Milah is weightier. Why is מילה Milah
weightier? Because it's... and what does תדירה במצות Tadyra b'mitzvos mean? So
רש"י Rashi says it just means that there's like, you know, it
says multiple times, like there's all these, you know, 13, you know,
בריתות Britot it says by מילה, Milah, ברית, Brit, ברית, Brit, ברית,
Brit, although I don't know why that's associated with תדירה במצות Tadyra
b'mitzvos here. But anyway, you could just also say there's implications of
ברית מילה Brit Milah for multiple מצוות, Mitzvos, although not so many,
for פסח ותרומה. Pesach v'Trumah. Anyway, the point here is that the
phrase is being used very loosely. This is not the תדיר Tadyor
of precedence, this is just weightier. Okay, so ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eima,
and if you want, I can say מילה לגבי פסח כי תדיר
דמי, Milah legabei pesach ki tadyor dami, which seems to be the
same point. Like look, relative to something, we could say it's more
תדיר, Tadyor, although again it's ironic because פסח Pesach at least has
a regularity. Okay, but again, it is not a תדיר Tadyor that
is... that is important for our scale. That's being used very loosely
there, is basically the answer. Okay, so that's interesting, the difference between
תדיר Tadyor and מצוי. Matzui. So we don't have an answer to
the question, although let's face it, all of the evidence is תדיר
קודם. Tadyor kodem. I mean, there's a lot of weak answers, all
of the evidence is that תדיר Tadyor is קודם. Kodem. Okay, now
we get to the question of a variation of this question, okay,
which is going to be all the same evidence brought to answer
a different question. איבעיא להו. Iba'i lehu. They raised the following question.
תדיר ושאינו תדיר וקדם ושחט שאינו תדיר. Tadyor v'she'eino tadyor v'kodem ushachat
she'eino tadyor. You have a תדיר Tadyor and a not תדיר Tadyor
in front of you, okay, so... and you went ahead and you
shachted the wrong one first. Okay, so... so, let's say you had,
I don't know, שבת Shabbos and ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Okay, so...
right, 'cause שבת Shabbos is תדיר. Tadyor. So and we've established that
שבת Shabbos comes first. And you went ahead and
you shachted the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh first. You shachted the ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh first. Do you put aside throwing the blood of
the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh so you can get back to the
right order and do the שבת Shabbos first? Or do you say
once you shachted it and you're dealing with the blood, it would
be not respectful to put aside the blood and you just finish
the ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, the one you're in the middle of?
Okay, מאי, Mai, what do you say? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do
we say
כיון דשחטיה מקריב ליה, Kivan d'shachtei makriv lehu, since you've already shachted
the ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, go ahead and bring it? או דלמא,
O dilma, יהיב לאחרינא דממרס בדמא, Yahaiv l'acher d'mameris b'dama, no,
have somebody stir the blood and keep it from congealing עד דמקריב
ליה לתדיר, Ad d'makriv lei l'tadyor, and then go ahead and bring
שבת, Shabbos, now let's get back to the right order, והדר מקריב
לשאינו תדיר, V'hadar makriv l'she'eino tadyor, and go back to the one
that's שאינו תדיר. Eino tadyor. אמר רב הונא מסורא, Amar Rav Huna
mi-Sura, תא שמע. Ta shema. Okay, now it's going to be a
similar string of evidence. שלמים של אמש חטאת ואשם. Shlamim shel emesh,
chatas v'asham. שלמים של אמש חטאת ואשם של יום Shlamim shel emesh
chatas v'asham shel yom של אמש קודם shel emesh kodem if it
was yesterday's שלמים Shlamim and today's חטאת chatas and אשם, asham, you
bring yesterday's, and we're assuming it means it was brought yesterday and
you didn't שחט shecht it. הא דהיום דומיא דאמש Ha d'hayom dumya
d'emesh but if they were both brought today, but it was somewhat
similar to the scenario of שלמים Shlamim brought yesterday. What's a case
of brought today but similar to brought yesterday? והיכי דמי דקדם שחטיה
לשלמים. V'heichi dami d'kadam shachtei l'shlamim.
You already שחט shecht the שלמים. Shlamim. So that means that they're
both brought today, but שלמים Shlamim got its foot in the door
first. How'd it get its foot in the door first today? 'Cause
it was שחט shecht first. So to that the גמרא Gemara seems
like anything less radical than having been brought yesterday, you would do
the חטאת chatas first. So if they were both brought today, even
if you שחט shecht the שלמים, Shlamim, this is what we're inferring,
first you'd bring the חטאת chatas first. Okay. חטאת ואשם קודמי. Chatas
v'asham kodmi. So you see that yes, you do push it off
if it was שחט shecht first. So the גמרא Gemara says, now
that's again by the way, not an issue of תדיר. tadir. That's
an issue of קדוש. kadosh. But the גמרא Gemara understands that the
same would be true. The same question we could ask. You went
out of order. Whether your out of order was doing the אינו
תדיר eino tadir first or whether your out of order was doing
the lesser קדוש kadosh first. If you went out of order, what
do you do? Same question. Okay, and here it wants to infer
that by a שלמים Shlamim you put it aside, the blood, in
order to get the חטאת chatas and אשם asham first. So the
גמרא Gemara says, דילמא שלמים דאמש וחטאת ואשם דהיום היכי משכחת לה
דשחטינהו לתרווייהו. Dilma Shlamim d'emesh v'chatas v'asham d'hayom heichi mishkachas lah d'shachtinu
l'travaihu. No,
says the גמרא, Gemara, the scenario that they're both today, but that
the שלמים Shlamim jumped got its foot in the door first, is
you שחט shecht the שלמים Shlamim first, yes, I'll concede that, and
you שחט shecht the חטאת. chatas. So now you're dealing with both
of, I mean not first. And you שחט shecht the חטאת. chatas.
You שחט shecht the שלמים Shlamim first, but you didn't ask at
that stage. Then you went ahead and שחט shecht the חטאת. chatas.
At that stage, you're dealing with both of their bloods, I will
see and one blood has to be postponed, I'll say push off
the שלמים. Shlamim. Okay, 'cause one of the bloods is going to
have to be postponed. אבל לא שחטינהו לתרווייהו, Aval lo shachtinu l'travaihu,
if you only שחט shecht the שלמים Shlamim and you haven't שחט
shecht yet the חטאת, chatas, then תיבעי לך tibei lach that is
not, you cannot infer that from the משנה. Mishna. Okay. So it
is not clear if you already got the blood of one, do
you push that off in order to get back to the right
order or not? Whether that order is תדיר tadir or the order
is קדוש. kadosh. Let's just go further. דבר אחר. Davar acher. ברכת
היין תדירה, Birkas hayayin tadira, ברכת היום אינה תדירה. Birkas hayom eina
tadira.
So again, between בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri hagafen and מקדש השבת.
mekadesh haShabbos. Now it assumes that שבת Shabbos begins before you're dealing
with wine. So it's like you sort of שחט shecht the קרבן
korban already. You've already engaged שבת. Shabbos. And now you're pushing aside
the acknowledgment of שבת Shabbos in order to get wine in the
door. It's a similar type of a thing. Okay, you've already encountered
שבת, Shabbos, you should acknowledge it first. But no, we're going to
push it aside to let the wine be introduced first. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אינה תדירה ותדיר ושאינו תדיר תדיר קודם. eina
tadira v'tadir v'sheino tadir tadir kodem.
So the גמרא Gemara answer is, הכא נמי כיון דאתין כמאן דשחטינהו
לתרווייהו דמי. hacha nami keivan d'asien k'man d'shachtinhu l'travaihu dami. Since you
put the wine on the table and you have a cup filled
with wine, so now you're encountering wine as well. So it's like
you שחט shecht the שלמים Shlamim and you שחט shecht the חטאת.
chatas. It's true you encountered שבת Shabbos first, okay, but now you're
dealing with both of them having each having been encountered, although שבת
Shabbos was encountered first. So you're going to have to push aside
one of the things you've already encountered. It's not your only pushing
aside שבת. Shabbos. If you were to do שבת Shabbos first, you
would be pushing aside the wine. So in that case what do
you do?
Did you pour the, they're trying to say if you didn't pour
the cup of wine you should say something about שבת?
Shabbos? No, but you can't start saying קידוש Kiddush without having poured
the cup of wine. Okay, what's this? One moment, let's finish this.
Okay, okay, תא שמע Ta shma come and hear. אמר רבי יוחנן
Amar Rabbi Yochanan הלכה מתפלל אדם של מנחה ואחר כך של מוספין.
halacha mispalel adam shel Mincha v'achar kach shel Musafin.
So the גמרא Gemara says מנחה Mincha first even though you encountered
the obligation of מוסף Musaf first. So look, you're pushing aside the
obligation of מוסף Musaf which you encountered first in order to do
מנחה Mincha which is the right order. So the same answer. הכא
נמי כיון דמטא זמן תפילת מנחה, Hacha nami keivan d'mata zman tfilas
Mincha, no, now you're at מנחה Mincha time you now have also
encountered מנחה Mincha כמאן דשחטינהו לתרווייהו דמי. k'man d'shachtinhu l'travaihu dami. Now
you've encountered both, so you're either you're going to be putting one
aside. It's still not like the case where you haven't שחט shecht
the חטאת chatas yet. Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב אשי
לרבינא. Amar lei Rav Acha breih d'Rav Ashi l'Ravina. Okay, so fine.
So that's the answer, we went through the same proofs and we
haven't proven it so we don't know the answer to that question
either. Yes, Charlie.
Thinking practically, I'm not, I don't know if you have this case
of the שלמים Shlamim and the חטאת, chatas, I don't understand what
the problem would be. They can be slaughtered in different places, there's
sprinklings in different places on the מזבח. mizbeach.
Yeah, it's a good point. You mean why do you have to
choose? You have to create a scenario in which
two כהנים kohanim in the,
you have to create a scenario in which all the other כהנים
kohanim are busy. But you're right. I mean the גמרא Gemara isn't
asking that practical question, but it's a very good point. Since when
do you have to choose? You have a lot of people there,
have them all do everything. Okay. Maybe it's even a question of
which one do you assign, but you're right. The fact that it
says stir the blood, right? Why don't you, you know, even if
the question of like who do I assign first, do I first
assign this or assign that? You're right. You have to have a
scenario in which there's a shortage of כהנים. kohanim. All the כהנים
kohanim went out for an emergency, there's two כהנים kohanim left in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, anyway, but it's a good point.
Okay, now let's wrap this up. תא שמע, Ta shma, where were
we? Okay, אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב. Amar lei Rav Acha
breih d'Rav. תא Tash where are we? Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא
בריה דרב אשי לרבינא: Amaleih Rav Achah brei deRav Ashi l'Ravina: שחטו
קודם חצות פסול, Shachtu kodem chatzos pasul, מפני שנאמר בין הערבים. mipnei
shene'emar bein ha'arbayim.
So here we're trying to go and prove it. שחטו Shachtu the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach before חצות chatzos is פסול pasul because it
says between the evenings. קודם לתמיד כשר. Kodem letamid kasher. If you
slaughtered it before the תמיד tamid של shel the afternoon תמיד, tamid,
you're supposed to slaughter the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach after the afternoon
תמיד. tamid. Okay, because it says ערב erev twice by פסח, Pesach,
which means the latest thing in the day even though the afternoon
תמיד tamid is usually the last thing. But בדיעבד, bedieved, if you
slaughtered it before the afternoon תמיד tamid it's כשר. kasher. Okay, and
what do you do? ויעמם בדם עד שיזרוק הדם. Veyamem bedam ad
sheyizrok hadam. But we want to still get the תמיד tamid in
earlier, so have somebody stir the blood of the פסח Pesach until
somebody else can throw the blood of the תמיד. tamid. So here,
you went out of order, and when you went out of order
you see what you're supposed to do? You're supposed to have somebody
stir the blood and return to the normal order of things. So
this seems to be pretty darn good evidence that you'd get someone
to stir the blood so you could restore the normal order. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא במאי עסקינן כגון ששחט לתמיד ברישא.
hacha bemai askinan kegon sheshachat letamid bereisha. No, no, no. If you
haven't slaughtered the תמיד tamid yet, I might say throw the blood,
and then get around to the תמיד, tamid, don't restore the order.
The case we're dealing with is you slaughtered the תמיד. tamid. So
you slaughtered the פסח Pesach first, which you shouldn't have done, then
you slaughtered the תמיד, tamid, and now you have to choose which
blood to do first. In that case, restore the order since one
of the bloods is going to have to be postponed. Okay. אמר
ליה אביי ולימא ליה רב אשי מתניתין דייקא. Amaleih Abaye v'leima leih
Rav Ashi masnisin dayka. You know what? Even though that seems like
an אוקימתא, okimta, it actually there's a, you that seems to be
consistent with a close read of that משנה. Mishnah. Why? דקתני De-ktani
עד שיזרוק הדם. ad sheyizrok hadam. It says stir the blood of
the פסח Pesach till you throw the blood of the תמיד. tamid.
Which sounds like you started dealing with the blood of the תמיד.
tamid. ולא קתני, V'lo ktani, it didn't say עד שישחוט ויזרוק דם.
ad sheyishchot veyizrok dam. Why didn't it say stir the blood of
the פסח Pesach and then slaughter the תמיד tamid and throw the
blood? It didn't say that. So since it didn't say that, it
sounds like maybe if you hadn't slaughtered the תמיד tamid yet, you
would finish the פסח. Pesach. And we're dealing with a scenario, we
don't know, and we're dealing with a scenario you slaughtered the תמיד,
tamid, it just you did it second and now you have to
push aside one of the bloods, so in that case restore the
order. But if you haven't slaughtered it we don't know whether what's
more important, to restore the order or to finish up with what
you've started with. So again a question that has not been resolved.
ובכולן כהנים רשאים, Uvechulan kohanim rashaim, the כהנים kohanim can add whatever
spices they want and cook it in any way they want. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
You're allowed to bring spices from home, you know.
Yeah exactly. You know you imagine you have a little pantry there
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Wait a minute, where's my cilantro?
You
know anyway. Okay. חולין בעזרה. Chullin ba'azarah. Right. Well that's a good
point, there's only קרבנות, korbanos, right? Right, it's only, that's a good
point. I mean I think there's a תוספות Tosafos that asks about
the חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah question, but yes it's bringing חולין בעזרה
chullin ba'azarah is usually in the context of הקרבה. hakravah. Okay. מאי
טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר קרא למשחה. Amar kra le-moshchah.
It says I have given them to you for משחה moshchah for
anointing or for status, לגדולה, legdulah,
so it means that you can eat it like in a sense
of you know of importance. And importance maybe you say oh it's
only fancy is only prepared this way. כדרך שהמלכים אוכלין, Kederech shehamelachim
ochlin, the way kings eat. So you know, so you're going to
say maybe that only means if it's done in a very fancy
way. But you know as what's his name famously said Mel Brooks,
it's good to be king. You can, if you're a king you
can eat it whatever way you want, nobody else gets to complain.
But it is interesting right, you could have said maybe you're not
allowed to eat it raw, you're not allowed to eat it double
boiled. Double boiled is the way sick people eat, it's not the
way you know fancy. So it's very interesting the translation of status,
status is I guess not the same as fancy. If you really
are of important enough you get to decide what we're having for
dinner, you know and nobody else gets to complain.
And the only exception of course is קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Very
exactly. Okay. Is he not going to address about the תבלי תרומה
tavlei terumah at all?
We addressed that earlier. המביא קצת לידי פסול. Hamevi k'tzas lidei pasul.
That was directly discussed in that earlier סוגיא. sugya. אמר רבי שמעון:
Amar Rabbi Shimon: אם ראית שמן שמתחלק בעזרה. Im ra'isa shemen shemis-chalek
ba'azarah. Now
I don't know why we're getting onto this point here. I mean
again now we're dealing with how things I guess are eaten. Somehow
you know we moved from this precedent to mentioning eating and now
we're focusing on how things are eaten. So he said if you
saw in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash כהנים kohanim like dividing up
a container of oil, that oil was brought in some context of
a קרבן korban that now the כהנים kohanim are eating it. What's
the context? When is oil brought to the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
I mean it's mixed with a מנחה. mincha. But when is it
brought by itself that then would be eaten by the כהנים? kohanim?
So he says I'll tell you. אין צריך לשאול מהו, Ein tzarich
lishol mahu, you don't have to say hey what's going on with
that oil?
אלא מותר רקיקי מנחות ישראל. Ella mosar rekikei minchos Yisrael. There's two
possibilities. Either it's one of a רקיק, rekik, one of the breads
when you bring a type of a
מנחה, mincha, so you basically you, you know, you just do a
little bit of oil on a wafer like a little X of
oil on a wafer and you have leftover all the rest of
the oil that you didn't use in the baking of that מנחה,
mincha, certain type of a מנחה. mincha. A רקיק rekik like the
wafer. Okay, so either it's the oil that's brought with the wafer
which is not really, most of the oil is not used in
the מנחה, mincha, so the remainder is eaten by the כהנים. kohanim.
Or ולוג שמן של מצורע, v'log shemen shel metzora, the לוג log
of oil of a מצורע metzora which you use it for like
a certain application on the ear and whatever and then the rest
is eaten by the כהנים. kohanim. Those are the two ways you'll
get oil eaten in the עזרה azarah straight. אם ראית שמן שניתן
על גבי אישים, Im ra'isa shemen shenitan al gabei ishim, now let's
say you see them throwing oil on the
fire. So that's adding fuel to the fire, but what's the reason?
Right? They bring it as a type of a קרבן. korban. So
אין צריך לשאול מה הוא. ein tzarich lishol mah hu. Hey, what's
that oil doing on the fire? אלא מותר רקיקי מנחות כהנים. Ella
motar rekikei minchos kohanim. If you've got a רקיק, rakik, the same
מנחה mincha of a כהן, kohen, what's the הלכה? halacha? A כהן,
kohen, everything is burnt. So you have the same reality, most of
the oil is not mixed with the מנחה, mincha, but rather than
being eaten because it's a מנחה mincha of a כהן, kohen, it's
all burnt.
ומנחת כהן משיח U'minchas kohen mashiach and the מנחה mincha of the
כהן גדול kohen gadol that he brings every day, which also is
a type of a, let me just see, רש"י Rashi explains why
there's a lot of that.
Yeah, because for him, there is a large quantity of oil, disproportionate
amount of oil that the תורה Torah assigns for the מנחה mincha
of a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. And therefore, because there too, it's
not going to all be mixed with the מנחה. mincha. So again,
because it's a מנחה mincha of a כהן, kohen, here כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, it all gets burnt. Because the amount of oil is
very, very high proportionally, it's not all mixed with the flour, so
it'll be burnt by itself.
Okay. Now שאין מתנדבין שמן. she'ein misnadvim shemen. But I will tell
you what it isn't. It is not somebody who סתם stam decided
I'm going to give
a free will offering of oil, I'm going to give a נדבה
nedava of oil. Because you're not allowed to do that. The תורה
Torah doesn't recognize oil as a type of a קרבן korban by
itself. Okay? So it's going to come from these other קרבנות. korbanos.
One minute. רבי טרפון אומר מתנדבין שמן. Rabbi Tarfon omer misnadvim shemen.
Rabbi Tarfon says, 'Ah, no, actually, I think it could be a
נדבה. nedava. I think it's possible to do a נדבה nedava of
just pure oil.' It's not mentioned in the תורה, Torah, so we're
going to see in the גמרא Gemara where you learn that out
from.
Did you want to say something? Rabbi... about the עצים, eitzim, right?
Weren't you allowed to also have a קרבן עצים? korban eitzim?
Yeah, yeah, so all of these are different opinions about expanding the
scope of קרבנות. korbanos. Rabbi Shimon... wait, if you're allowed to have
עצים, eitzim, you were allowed to... yeah, but I don't know if
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees to that either. אמר שמואל לדברי רבי
טרפון. Amar Shmuel lidivrei Rabbi Tarfon. Now here's what we want to
know before we even get to the question about what the source
is, although this is going to engage the question of what the
source is. If you can give a שמן shemen offering, is it
like an עולה olah or is it like a מנחה? mincha? What
do you do with the oil? Do you offer some and eat
the rest? There were two scenarios in the משנה mishna with what
was being done with oil. And the כהנים kohanim eat the rest,
you don't, right? Right, and the כהנים kohanim eat the rest, or
does it all get burnt? Right? Because we were dealing with two
scenarios which can exist by different types of קרבנות, korbanos, but in
the context of the נדבה, nedava, we didn't say which box it
would fit into.
Okay? So שמואל Shmuel says לדברי רבי טרפון המתנדב שמן. lidivrei Rabbi
Tarfon hamisnadeiv shemen. If you offer up, if you give a נדבה
nedava of oil, קומצו, komzo, you do a קומץ kometz on the
oil. Your hands are going to get very icky. Okay? I don't
know. Yeah, I don't know. And how much stays in your hand?
I don't know.
ושיריו נאכלים Veshiyurei ne'echalim and you put that קומץ kometz on the
fire and the rest, you treat it like a מנחה, mincha, the
rest is eaten. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אמר קרא,
Amar krah, because we learn it out from a פסוק pasuk by
מנחה. mincha. קרבן מנחה, Korban mincha, a קרבן korban of a מנחה
mincha it says, you know, תקריבו אותם. takrivu osam. Why didn't it
just say מנחה? mincha? What's the extra word קרבן? korban? So the
extra word קרבן korban is to tell you there's something else that
is like a מנחה mincha that can be its own קרבן, korban,
and that's somehow we learn that that's oil. מלמד שמתנדבין שמן. Melamed
shemisnadvim shemen. I don't know, well we're going to get to one
in a minute. Why can't it be flour? You know, if you're
learning it out from the מנחה, mincha, so, you know, if you
could have a pure flour thing, so I mean you have flour
without the oil. Anyway, okay. וכי מנחה, Vechi mincha, but if מנחות
minchos are base, it has to follow that model, or is our
source? מה מנחה קומץ ושיריו נאכלים אף שמן קומץ ושיריו נאכלים. Mah
mincha kometz veshiyurav ne'echalim af shemen kometz veshiyurav ne'echalim. Okay, so you
do some on the... you do a קומץ kometz and that gets
burnt and the rest gets eaten.
Wait, what's this וכי מנחה? vechi mincha?
It's just like a מנחה. mincha. Since our source is
מנחה, mincha, it's...
not quoting any פסוק? pasuk?
No, no, just like a מנחה. mincha. וכמנחה, Ukemincha, it's sort of
like that thing. אמר רב זירא אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rav
Zeira af anan nami tanina. That's implicit in our משנה. mishna. אמר
רבי שמעון אם ראית שמן שמתחלק בעזרה אי אתה צריך לשאול מה
הוא אלא מותר רקיקי מנחות ישראל Amar Rabbi Shimon im ra'isa shemen
shemis-chalek ba'azara iy atah tzarich lishol mah hu ella motar rekikei minchos
Yisrael ולא שמן המצורע velo shemen hametzora שאין מתנדבין שמן. she'ein misnadvim
shemen. Okay, because his first example in the משנה mishna is oil
being eaten, and he says I'm telling you that this is coming
from like a רקיק rakik or whatever, because it's not coming from
a נדבה. nedava. The implication being that רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon who
says it could be coming from a נדבה nedava would understand that
a נדבה nedava would be eaten. מכלל דמאן דאמר מתנדבין מתחלק, Michlal
deman de'amar misnadvim mis-chalek, it would be divided and eaten. Of course
that's not great because the משנה mishna has two scenarios, one of
being eaten, one of being burnt, right? It's not clear what this
is exactly the question. When רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says it could
be a נדבה, nedava, which scenario is he referring to? The one
of it being eaten or the one of it being burnt? אמר
ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, Abaye said אימא סיפא. eima seifa. Wait,
wait, wait, you can't say that, because the second case is being
burnt.
אם ראית שמן שניתן גבי האישים אי אתה צריך לשאול מה הוא
אלא מותר רקיקי מנחות כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח Im ra'isa shemen she'nittan
gabei ha'ishim iy atah tzarich lishol mah hu ella motar rekikei minchos
kohanim u'minchas kohen mashiach שאין מתנדבין שמן. she'ein misnadvim shemen. Because it
can't be a נדבה, nedava, because you don't do... this is רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, because you don't give a נדבה nedava of oil.
מכלל דמאן דאמר מתנדבין לאישים, Michlal deman de'amar misnadvim le'ishim, according to
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon it says you give a נדבה nedava of
oil, כולו לאישים, kulo le'ishim, it would go on the fire. So
there are two scenarios in the משנה, mishna, and then רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon says, 'No, no, no, I think it could be a
נדבה.' nedava. Which scenario is he referring to?
So now
the
גמרא Gemara says לאביי קשיא רישא. le'Abaye kashya reisha. that רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon would allow for? And for רב זירא Rav Zeira that
says it's eaten, what do you do for the second scenario? So
the גמרא Gemara says it's much easier for רב זירא. Rav Zeira.
בשלמא דרב זירא רישא בשיריים סיפא בקומץ. bishlama de-Rav Zeira reisha b'shiurayim
seifa b'komets. For רב זירא Rav Zeira it makes sense. Okay, you
have sometimes oil that is a נדבה nedavah for רבי טרפון, Rabbi
Tarfon, oil is a נדבה, nedavah, both could be eaten and could
be burned. Why? The קומץ komets of it is burned, the remainder
of it is eaten. Okay, so for רב זירא Rav Zeira it
reads very simple. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says here are the types
of קרבנות korbanot oil could be, but it can't be a נדבה,
nedavah, okay, but it could be this way, it could be eaten
and this way it could be burned but not a נדבה. nedavah.
And רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says it could be a נדבה nedavah
and in a נדבה nedavah some of it will be burned and
some of it will be eaten. It works very nice for רב
זירא. Rav Zeira. But for אביי, Abaye, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is
only disagreeing with the second scenario of burned. He would not disagree
with the first scenario because he doesn't have a נדבה nedavah that's
eaten. אלא אביי קשיא, ela Abaye kashya, for אביי Abaye what do
you do with the first scenario where it's eaten if רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon doesn't hold that מנחת נדבה minchat nedavah שמן נדבה shemen
nedavah is eaten? תני רישא אטו סיפא, tani reisha atu seifa, you're
right, we only mentioned the first scenario because we're going to have
the second one but the debate is about the second scenario. רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon agrees to the first scenario of being eaten. So
the גמרא Gemara says
בשלמא סיפא תני משום רישא, bishlama seifa tani mishum reisha, and the
גמרא Gemara says I don't buy that. You could say we started
with scenario one, that was the focus, and then we threw in
scenario two. אלא רישא משום סיפא מי תני? ela reisha mishum seifa
mi tani? But if the real focus of the issue in the
משנה Mishnah was the second scenario, why start with the first one
if everybody agrees to it? Right? I mean maybe start with the
one they debate and then throw in a second one. So the
גמרא Gemara says אין, in, yes, אמרי במערבא amrei be-ma'arava they say
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael תני רישא משום סיפא tani reisha mishum
seifa sometimes we do that. We lead in and you could understand
that, right, it actually makes sense. Here's scenario number one, everybody agrees
to this scenario. It actually makes a lot of sense. Now let's
talk about scenario number two. In scenario number two there's a debate.
Right? I say it's only burnt as part of a קרבן, korban,
another קרבן, korban, and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says it could be
burnt even by itself. Okay, so there you have that debate. Is
this שמן shemen of נדבה nedavah for רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon like
a מנחה, minchah, some of it is burnt, the majority of it
is eaten? Or is it like a type of an עולה olah
and it all gets burnt, that's what אביי Abaye wants to argue?
And therefore for אביי, Abaye, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon would only be
disagreeing by the second scenario. So we're not done, we're going to
continue to try to prove it. It's confusing sometimes when they have
two dots because you think the discussion is over and it's not.
תא שמע, ta shema, יין כדברי רבי עקיבא לספלים. yayin ke-divrei Rabbi
Akiva le-sfalim. So now there's a position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
as Michael correctly noted, the idea that you can bring other types
of קרבנות korbanot that are not mentioned in the תורה Torah is
not limited to oil, there's also a famous debate of can you
bring just wine? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says yes, you could
be מנדב menadeiv just plain wine. So what do you do with
that wine? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you pour it down
the...
oh wait, sorry, is that
just Rabbi Akiva
or another מחלוקת machloket not cited here that if you bring wine
may also... we'll get to that
possibility of
wine
going on the
fire. But right now, anyway, right now what
the point is is that presumably the same way you pour all
the wine
down the funnel, the meaning that it goes to the fire means
you put all of the
oil on the
fire, okay. מאי לאו מדי
יין כולו לספלים
שמן כולו לאישים?
mai lav mi-de-yayin kulo
le-sfalim shemen kulo la-ishim? Since the wine all goes down the funnel,
we say when we say the
oil goes on the fire, we mean all of the oil? And
that's a
support of אביי.
Abaye. So the גמרא Gemara says מידי אירייא? mi-di irya? What, that's
a proof? הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא. ha ke-dita ve-ha ke-dita. Each one
its own way.
Wine is all poured down the funnel, the oil, the oil that
you put on the מזבח mizbe'ach goes on the fire but the
rest of the oil is eaten. That doesn't prove אביי Abaye over
רב זירא, Rav Zeira, that just means some of the oil is
going
on the fire. אמר רב פפא כתנאי, amar Rav Papa ke-tana'ei, this
question about what you do with the oil
I'm going to say is... How can you separate
these? Each one,
each one
its own way. Wine is all poured down the funnel, but oil,
the oil that you put on the altar goes on the fire,
but the rest of the oil is eaten. That doesn't prove אביי
Abaye over רבי זירא. Rebbe Zeira. That just means some of the
oil is going on the fire. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
כתנאי, kitna'i, this question about what you do with the oil, I'm
going to say is linked to a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. שמן
לא יפחות מלוג. Shemen lo yifchos milog.
How much oil? If you say a מנדב menadev in oil, what's
the minimum amount that we can, that you can give if you
don't specify?
So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says no less than a לוג,
log, because that's the normal amount that went with a מנחה. Mincha.
רבי אומר שלושה לוגין, Rebbi omer shloshas lugin, three לוג. log. Now
three לוג log is the minimum amount of oil that comes with
a מנחת נסכים. Minchas Nesachim. Okay? רביעית ההין לשמן לכבש... Revi'is HaHin
LaShemen LaKeves... no that's יין, yayin, excuse me.
It's the minimum amount of wine, excuse me, that comes with a
what do you call it, with a מנחת נסכים. Minchas Nesachim. Okay?
A הין Hin is twelve לוג log and a רביעית ההין revi'is
haHin is three לוג. log. Okay? So רבי Rebbi is going to
be the interesting one because the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma saying a
לוג log is obvious, that's the amount of שמן shemen that comes
with a מנחה. Mincha. So במאי קמיפלגי? be-mai kamifligi? What's this debate
about? אמרו בני קמיה דרב פפא, Amru b'nei kammai de-Rav Pappa, so
the rabbis sort of said in front of רב פפא: Rav Pappa:
דון מינה ומינה don mina u-mina and דון מינה ואוקי באתרה. don
mina u-uki b'atrah. I love this question. When you apply learning from
A to B, do you take A, right, it's like normally a
גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah case, okay? Here we have scenario A and
here we have scenario B, and I'm going to learn this הלכה
halacha that exists in A also applies in B. When I apply
it to B, do I take it with its entire context of
A? Do I take the whole package and I apply it in
B with its original context, or do I apply it in B
with the context of B? So to take it with its context
is דון מינה ומינה. don mina u-mina. You learn from it and
you take with it its original context. If you apply to it
the context of B, you know, you only learned the one הלכה,
halacha, but once that one הלכה halacha gets incorporated here, all of
the rest of the הלכות halachos follow the application. That's דון מינה
ואוקי באתרה. don mina u-uki b'atrah. Take it from it and then
establish it in its place. Sort of like the question about whether
America is the great melting pot or is it the salad bowl,
okay? Right? Multiculturalism or what's the opposite of multiculturalism? Anyway,
do
things maintain
their original sort of identities, or do they get assimilated into... that's
really what it is, multiculturalism versus assimilation. Now you can tell people
that's what I learned today in the דף, Daf, a מחלוקת machlokes
about multiculturalism versus assimilation. Okay, so דון מינה ומינה don mina u-mina
or דון מינה ואוקי באתרה. don mina u-uki b'atrah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: איכא בינייהו. Ika beinihu.
דרבנן סברי, de-Rabbanan savri, מה מנחה, mah Mincha, you learn it from
a מנחה. Mincha. Okay? So since מנחה Mincha is the source of
the idea of wine, of oil, it applies to the laws of
a מנחה Mincha and the amount of oil in a מנחה Mincha
is a לוג. log. מה מנחה משתנדבין אף שמן משתנדבין, mah Mincha
misnadvin af shemen misnadvin, the same way a מנחה Mincha is a
נדבה, nedava, אף שמן משתנדבין. af shemen misnadvin. ומינה, u-mina, and you
maintain the original context. מה מנחה לוג שמן אף כאן לוג. mah
Mincha log shemen af kan log. It's a לוג. log. And so
that's their position. Logically, of course, what then follows from that position,
if the whole basis and framing is a מנחה, Mincha, is that
that's also what you do with the oil. ומה מנחה קומץ ושירי
נאכלין, u-mah Mincha kometz ve-shiyarei ne'echalin, the same way, now this is
now not stated in the debate, but now we're going to say
why it's relevant to our issue, because if מנחה Mincha applies the
whole, is the source of the whole context, the same way by
מנחה Mincha you take a קומץ kometz and you eat the remnant,
אף שמן קומץ ושירי נאכלין. af shemen kometz ve-shiyarei ne'echalin. That would
be the position of the רבנן. Rabbanan.
So they say if the לוג log is the voice of the
רבנן... Rabbanan...
no, no, no, we're trying to figure out within... yes, yes, these
are two opinions within רבי טרפון, Rebbi Tarfon, okay? But we're trying
to figure out within, would רבי טרפון's Rebbi Tarfon's idea of שמן
shemen be like a קומץ kometz or would it all be burnt?
So we're saying actually that depends on these two opinions within רבי
טרפון, Rebbi Tarfon, within שמן, shemen, of whether it's a לוג log
or whether it's three לוג. log. If it's a לוג, log, you're
using מנחה Mincha as your entire structure. And if you're using מנחה
Mincha as your entire structure, you do a קומץ kometz and you
eat the rest, right? So this is all a debate within רבי
טרפון. Rebbi Tarfon. Okay, ורבי... ve-Rebbi... where are we?
Okay. ואידך, ve-idach, and the other one, meaning רבי Rebbi would say,
ממנחה, mi-Mincha, yes, you learn from מנחה Mincha the idea that you
do a לוג, log, that you have oil by itself. מה מנחה
Mincha. משתנדבין אף שמן shemen משתנדבין. ואוקי באתרה, ve-uki b'atrah, but now
it is, you know, it assimilates, it takes on the normal context
of that it's being applied to. כנסכים. ke-nesachim. So now that it
is something that is a liquid, I don't know why this is
באתרה, be-atrah, but okay, we're sort of somehow assuming that a נסכים
nesachim is like רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, that we're already assuming that
you do oil by itself, or somehow we're looking at it like
some type of a liquid. So now it has the context of
liquids that are offered up. So the only thing to compare it
to now is the wine. מה נסכים שלושה לוגין, mah nesachim shlosha
lugin, and the same way the minimum amount of wine is three
לוג, log. okay, אף שמן שלושה לוגין. af shemen shlosha lugin. So
שמן shemen is three לוג. log, So this is, this context is
liquids that are offered, okay, and this is מנחה.
mincha. Everyone will agree that wine, if it's offered, is a certain...
presumably, okay, although now... So where even just talking when it's liquid
even if it's offered as part of another קרבן. korban. So שמן
now gets applied to a context of liquids that are offered. Do
you apply the context of liquids that are offered as, so therefore
you do three לוג, log or do you apply it like, no,
no, no, it's offered as its own liquid, but fundamentally it's learned
from a מנחה. mincha So if we're going to apply it to
the three לוג log and look at it from liquids that are
offered, we also should apply to it: what do you do with
it? You put it all on the fire, the same way by
the liquids, although you don't put them on the fire, but you
do put them all on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, אף שמן כולו
לאישים, af shemen kulo l'ishim, and ומה נסכים שלשת לוגין אף שמן
שלשת לוגין, u'ma nesachim sheloshet lugin af shemen sheloshet lugin, and מה
נסכים, ma nesachim, and now this is how it applies to our
debate, כולם לספלים אף שמן כולם לאישים. kulam l'sefalim af shemen kulam
l'ishim. So the debate of three and one is essentially a debate
of: do you learn from מנחה mincha? or do you learn from
wine? And that debate should translate into whether you eat most of
it or whether you put it all on the altar. So that
seems to be a good group. אמר ליה רב פפא, amar lei
Rav Pappa, so Rav Pappa said back: by the way, but
even if you do eat part of it, they're still both agreeing
that the part that goes on is the ספלים sefalim and not
actually the fire, right? What are they saying? Meaning we have a
מחלוקת machloket whether we eat most of it or
whether it all goes on the fire.
Right, but when we say fire, we actually mean fire, or we
mean ספלים? sefalim? No, fire. Okay, is it all connected to חטאת
השמן chatat hashemen in terms of all of it going up or
not all of it going up?
Yeah, exactly. Is it like an עולה, olah, or you think like
an עולה olah or like a מנחה? mincha, But you could say
is it like an עולה olah or like a חטאת, chatat, yeah,
exactly.
So the bunch that says part of it gets eaten and part
of it goes on the מזבח, mizbeach, we'd say that that part
that goes on the מזבח mizbeach is
on the fire.
Everybody's saying the fire, yeah.
So we say ספלים sefalim then?
No, ספלים sefalim is just the יין. yayin. Okay, it's not exactly
identical. Now, אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye.
Now, the now this is a little bizarre because רב פפא Rav
Pappa said this is a debate of תנאים, tannaim, okay? And then
the rabbis of his בית מדרש beit midrash explained it in this
way, okay? So that the three and one debate is a debate
of whether it's all on the fire or only a קומץ kometz
on the fire. Then the same רב פפא Rav Pappa who said
this is a debate of תנאים, tannaim, now he goes back and
he sort of
re-, seems like he modifies his position. Let's take a look. So
רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי: Abaye: אם ממנחה מייתי לה
רבי, im mimincha maytei lah Rabbi, if actually the context we all
agreed you were learning it from מנחה, mincha then דכולי עלמא דון
מינה ומינה. d'chulei alma don mina u'mina. Everybody would agree that you
take the original context and רבי Rabbi is not, you know, might
be of the principle you maintain the original context, okay? So his
idea of three is not because he learns it from מנחה mincha,
and then applies the rule of the wine. If he learned it
from מנחה, mincha he would keep the idea of מנחה mincha and
he would say only one לוג log? and maybe he would say
only the קומץ kometz goes on the fire. So why does רבי
Rabbi say three לוג? log Not because he learns from מנחה mincha.
and then has it assimilate, okay? אלא רבי מאזרח גמר לה. ela
Rabbi me'ezrach gamar lah. Okay, the פסוק pasuk basically says by wine
it says what's the פסוק? pasuk? Does somebody call the פסוק pasuk
there? It says, it says, נו. nu. Anyway, there's a פסוק pasuk
about bringing a כל האזרח, kol ha'ezrach, something about אזרח ezrach bringing
the wine, bringing the מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim. So I, רש"י Rashi
quoted it, I can't find the רש"י Rashi now. None of your
none of all your helpful Englishes there bring it down? Okay.
Whatever.
Anyway, there's a פסוק pasuk by the מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim that
says אזרח. ezrach. All right, so anyway, the point is we didn't
learn it from מנחה.
mincha כל האזרח יעשה ככה. kol ha'ezrach ya'aseh kacha.
כל האזרח יעשה ככה, kol ha'ezrach ya'aseh kacha, thank you. Okay, anyway,
so, so, anyway, this seems to be like a parenthetical point, okay?
We're still saying רב פפא Rav Pappa is still claiming it's a
debate of תנאים: tannaim: either you learn it from מנחה mincha and
it's only a קומץ, kometz, or you learn it from the liquids
like the wine and it's going to be, and it's going to
be the whole thing, okay? So the position of one, but the
only question is, is the debate whether that you learn it from
the מנחה mincha, and apply it here and the context takes over,
or is it no, actually the debate is, do you learn it
straight from מנחה, mincha, from קרבן מנחה, korban mincha, and then it's
going to be one לוג log and you only do a קומץ
kometz on the fire, or are you going to learn it straight
from the wine because it says אזרח ezrach by the מנחת נסכים,
minchat nesachim, and that אזרח ezrach is going to include actually oil
and therefore it's going to be three and all burnt? So it's
still the same point. If you're learning it from here, it's three
לוג log and it's all burnt, all burnt, and if you're learning
it from here, from מנחה, mincha it's one לוג log and it's
only a קומץ kometz on the fire, okay? So, and the question
is, what would make you learn it from here or here? So
from here, you would learn it from the פסוק pasuk about what
do you call it, קרבן מנחה, korban mincha,
and here you would learn it from the פסוק pasuk where it
says כל האזרח יעשה ככה. kol ha'ezrach ya'aseh kacha. So, so, anyway,
this seems to be like a parenthetical point, okay? We're still saying
רב פפא Rav Pappa is still claiming it's a debate of תנאים.
tannaim. Either you learn it from מנחה mincha and it's only a
קומץ, kometz, or you learn it from the liquids like the wine
and it's going to be and it's going to be the whole
thing, okay? So the position of one, but the only question is,
is the debate whether that you learn it from the מנחה mincha
and apply it here and the context takes over, or is it
no, actually the debate is do you learn it straight from מנחה
mincha from קרבן מנחה korban mincha and then it's going to be
one לוג log and you only do a קומץ kometz on the
fire, or are you going to learn it straight from the wine
because it says אזרח ezrach by the מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim and
that אזרח ezrach is going to include actually oil and therefore it's
going to be three and all burnt? So it's still the same
point. If you're learning it from here it's three לוג log and
it's all burnt, all burnt, and if you're learning it from here
from מנחה Mincha, it's one לוג log. and it's only a קומץ
kometz on the fire, okay? So and the question is what would
make you learn it from here or here? So from here you
would learn it from the פסוק pasuk about what do you call
it קרבן מנחה korban mincha and here you would learn it from
the פסוק pasuk where it says כל האזרח יעשה ככה. kol ha'ezrach
ya'aseh kacha. is more fundamental. Do you learn the idea of oil
from מנחה, Mincha or do you learn the idea of oil from
wine? Same point though, this question about what you do with the
מנחה Mincha is tied into this debate
of three versus one.
Okay, let's just read one more line. I know it's already a
bit, but we'll read one more line. In the chat? No, we're
not going to go to the end of the chapter. We're going
to read one more line. Okay. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב
נתן לרב פפא: Amar leh Rav Huna breih de-Rav Natan le-Rav Papa:
מי מצית אמרת הכי? Mi matsita amrat hachi? How could you say
that? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, קרבן מנחה Korban Mincha מלמד שנתנדב עם שמן melamed
she-nitnadav im shemen וכמה שלשה לוגין. ve-chamah shloshah login. Wait,
we have a ברייתא baraita says that it learns from the פסוק
pasuk קרבן מנחה, Korban Mincha, so it learns from the מנחה Mincha.
context, but then it says three לוג. log מאן תנא דאמר שלשה
לוגין רבי? Man tana de-amar shloshah login Rebbi?
רבי Rebbi says three לוג log וקמייתי ליה מקרבן ve-kamayti leh mi-korban
and you're learning it from מנחה. Mincha, So you see, again, this
is just a technical point, this doesn't argue the basic framework, but
you see that this position is not learning it straight from wine.
It's learning it from מנחה, Mincha applying it to the context of
wine, and then wine takes over. So he says אמר ליה תניא
תניא. Amar leh tanya tanya. All right, you got a ברייתא, baraita,
you got a ברייתא, baraita, I can't argue with that. Okay, I
would rather think that it's a fundamental debate of where what's your
source, but it seems from this ברייתא baraita that we all agree
that מנחה is the source and then it's again this debate about
whether it's, you know, multiculturalism versus assimilation and if you believe in
assimilation then it takes on the context of wine and three לוג
and it's all burnt. Okay, so we will end with that, fine.
We will end with that and tomorrow we're going to see an
interesting debate about the wine that maybe you don't pour the wine
down the funnel, maybe you put the wine on the fire itself.
We'll pick up with that tomorrow.
Which is why I thought when I first read the תורה Torah
that that